It's funny. Visiting Final Fantasy 7 Remake
nearly 20 years after playing the
original release *really* put into
perspective how much of the original
just went over my head when I first
played it.
Because when Square presented a premise of
terrorists against an evil mega-corporation
corporation to a sheltered boy--
that boy being me--
I saw Robin Hood versus the Sheriff of
Nottingham, or the Rebel Alliance versus
the Galactic Empire.
To me, this starting point was more a
means to an end, with the "end" being
cool battles, cool set pieces, and an even
cooler silver-maned villain introduced in
the first few hours of playtime.
Now, 20 years after my original
playthrough, I went into Remake with
better critical thinking skills, a little
more worldliness, and--of course--
a longstanding adderall prescription.
I became positioned like a goalie,
arms up and ready to intercept whatever
Remake threw at me.
And when the dust of my Remake playthrough
settled, what do you think I found in my hand?
Radical left...
*politics...?*
[Music]
dead generations presents
Is Final Fantasy VII a Radical, Left-Wing
Game?
Hello, I'm Vik for dead generations and in
this video, i plan to go on a journey with you.
At the end of our journey we'll find an
answer to the question in the video
title, which we'll uncover by first
exploring the following two assertions:
1. There is a radical heart to
Final Fantasy VII.
and 2. Final Fantasy VII reflects
real-life radical left politics.
Before I go on, I will warn you that this
video contains extensive spoilers for
the entire Compilation of Final Fantasy
VII, which includes the original game,
Remake, InterMISSION, and other sequels,
prequels, spin-offs... Kingdom Hearts...
The Kids Are All Right...
I've read through a lot of articles, essays, book
chapters, and manifestos to write this video,
and you can see a list of the references
linked in the description below.
For the most part i tried to make sure
my sources weren't paywalled, and I
invite you to read, scrutinize, and most
importantly, *use* my sources as a
breadcrumb trail to learn more about
the stuff that I talk about.
That said feel free to teach me a thing
or ten in the comments,
especially if i've gotten something
wrong.
I have also added subtitles, time stamps, a
transcript, and all that fun stuff so take advantage!
Now, let's begin by taking a closer look at the
foundational elements of Final Fantasy VII's world building.
Chapter 1: Shinra and the Shitty pizza
Barret: "The upper world...a city on a plate...
It's 'cuz of that shitty 'pizza', that
people underneath are sufferin'!
And the city below is full of polluted air.
On topa that the reactor keeps
drainin' up all the energy."
Cloud: "Then why doesn't
everyone move on to the Plate?"
"Barret: Dunno. probably 'cuz they
ain't got no money. Or, maybe..."
'Cuz they love their land,
no matter how polluted it gets."
"Cloud: I know... no one lives in
the slums because they want to.
It's like this train. It can't run
anywhere except where its rails take it."
Remake introduces you to its most
prominent villain in the first few
minutes of gameplay. The Shinra Electric
Power Company, a mega-corporation that
literally uses the planet's lifeblood
to power their reactors.
You're also introduced to remake's
rendition of one of the most memorable
locations in all of video games: the city
of Midgar
There's an elevated section where
affluent and middle-class people live,
hundreds of feet above ground, and a
ground-level section littered with debris,
pollution, and of course poor people.
As the Midgar section of the game's
story progresses, you learn more about
the way the Shinra Company's remit is
closer to that of the nation-state than
that of the typical evil corporation:
It employs a large number of
Midgar's residents.
It maintains a police force in the form
of the Shinra Public Security Forces.
It builds housing and infrastructure for
the city's residents.
It deploys its own paramilitary forces
in the form of SOLDIER and spies in the
form of the Turks in shady interventions
around the world.
It's even publicly engaged in a war with
Wutai, another nation-state.
Midgar does have a Mayor, Domino who is more a Shinra
Company figurehead than a legitimate civil authority.
Let's begin to put all this into a wider
cultural and historic context. First off
a question i'm sure is on all of our
minds right now:
what's a city, anyway?
I'm going to draw heavily from Chapter 1
of 2017's Cities of Power by sociologist
Göran Therborn for this section and
everything I'll reference can be read,
for free, via Google Books Preview.
Link in the description below.
Now, Therborn begins with a quote by
the historian Lewis Mumford that seems
to be a succinct explanation that even a
toddler can understand.
A city is... um...
"a point of maximum concentration for the
power and culture of a community."
While Cities of Power is mostly
concerned with surveying real-world
capital cities, some of the lessons of that first chapter
are generalizable enough to our discussion on Midgar.
In the Mumford quote, "Power" has political
and economic dimensions.
We can understand "political power" as the
authority granted "by coercion and or
persuasion through institutions and
processes of government."
To contextualize Therborn's definition:
I live in a city, and I have no choice
but to defer to the political power
wielded by my city government in the
form of its management of public
utilities, command over an army of cops,
its maintenance of the sidewalks and
roads I use to travel, and so on.
Relevant to us is the idea that
political power in cities can exist
alongside political counter-power, which
might take the form of protest rallies,
opposition movement headquarters, and
so on.
We can understand "economic power" as the
concentration of capital--
engines of production like factories--
and wealth.
Power shapes cities in very important
ways including spatially.
For example, if a city center is secluded
from the periphery of a city, we can
infer an element of social exclusivity.
Therborn's characteristic example
being former South African apartheid
cities which had undeveloped wastelands
separating non-white townships from
white city centers.
Even topography can be interpreted as a
power gradient.
Therborn specifically cites pre-modern
Edo, Japan, which saw lords living on
hills and their retinue below them.
Our understanding of Midgar as a concentration of
power starts with three words: the Shinra Company
1. The company provides reactors and
manufacturing facilities, and is where
the majority of the city's wealth is
tied.
2. Politically, we recall that the
Shinra Company effectively acts as
Midgar's government, providing public
services and infrastructure, in addition
to having the city's Mayor in their
pocket.
Importantly, we should try to recognize
the existence of a political
counter-power in Midgar. The name escapes
me right now, but I'm thinking of an
environmental phenomenon, and I can't
quite recall it.
What? You're saying that I should know
since I wrote the script to this video?
Oh, you.
Anyway, let's come back to that one a
little later.
We've placed Midgar in a sociopolitical
context, and in doing this we've
reaffirmed the outsized role of the
Shinra Company as the city's literal and
figurative source of power.
Let's talk about this relationship. The
evil corporation is well-trodden ground
in fiction around the world, and it's
easy to see the trope as a sort of
creative rebellion against the omnipresence
of corporations in our day-to-day lives.
If you're watching this video you've
probably encountered charts like this
one, created by Oxfam in 2014, which shows us that
10 companies own a lot of food sold at supermarkets.
But more than a creative rebellion, the
trope is predicated on actual harmful
practices corporations have historically
engaged in.
We can relate a few examples to Shinra
and Midgar.
1. Company towns. Defined as a
town with its buildings, amenities, and
businesses being owned by a single
company, and particularly prevalent in
the United States in the late 18th
century and early 19th century,
the concept is rife with problems for
the people actually working there.
Workers were subject to poor living
conditions, and the rent for these living
spaces would be higher than rent in
surrounding areas.
As company towns were fairly isolated,
workers who might have undertaken long
distance migration to reach these towns didn't have
many options for making an equivalent wage elsewhere.
This bind gave workers little choice but
to essentially give back a portion of
their wages to the company in exchange
for lodging, goods and services
If this setup sounds deeply exploitative--
that's because it is.
And if workers deigned to organize and
strike in response to these unfair
conditions, the consequences would be
disastrous.
The Ludlow Massacre of 1914 demonstrated
this morbidly well, in which the Colorado
Fuel and Iron Company, owned by the
Rockefeller Family, brought in the
Colorado National Guard and its own
gunman to attack a camp of striking
miners from the United Mine Workers of
America.
This led to over a dozen miners, their
spouses, and their children being murdered.
We can interpret Remake's Midgar as the
highest stage of the company town.
It's a settlement that's effectively
owned by the Shinra Company, it's fairly
isolated from its closest neighboring
settlement, Kalm,
and the existence of the city cannot be
decoupled from its mako reactors.
There's a core of people who live in
Midgar so they can work on and maintain
those reactors, and everything else--
the police force, the housing, the
infrastructure, and even businesses like Sam's Delivery
Service either directly or indirectly serve that core.
The natural resources and wealth that
are extracted from the system end up
literally flowing upwards to the Shinra
Company HQ.
Boy, I sure am glad we're nearly a
century out from the era of towns like
Ludlow and, Final Fantasy VII is a work
of fiction.
Foxconn plant: Dismal working Conditions
that fanned a stir. "In a room where
more than five people can't sleep, fifteen of us
sleep together on the floor. We stick to one another."
"The worker who did not want to be identified said
she earned ₹11,500 per month per month and paid ₹130
per month for the hostel and food." "Several others
and I have had stomach pains and urinary tract
infections before." "They serve us food on
time but very little.
Some women stay hungry throughout the day."
Amazon Is Creating Company Towns Across the
United States. "These are entire families
employed by Amazon.
Many of them will be let go within weeks,
though many others will quit even sooner,
unable to endure the stress and strain of the
job." "A public high-school classroom designed to
resemble an Amazon facility with
students wearing Amazon logos on their
clothing as they memorize Amazon's
leadership principles."
Ahem. 2. Paramilitaries.
Multinationals have long been accused of
funding paramilitaries to brutally
enforce their profit-driven goals in
regions around the world.
Take the humble Chiquita banana. For
nearly a century, the past and present
incarnations of Chiquita brands
International have allegedly worked with
paramilitaries in Colombia to murder
union organizers, indigenous Mayan people
and other activists.
We can look further back at the British
East India Company, what we might consider
the world's first multinational corporation.
The company's activities led to the subjugation of the
region of Bengal in South Asia in the mid-18th century.
Bengal was then used as a staging ground for the conquest
of the rest of the subcontinent over the next century.
The looting of South Asia, the seizure of
its property and wealth, was executed by the
use of a private army trained and paid
by the Company.
The Shinra Company evokes this paradigm
of colonialism in their use of SOLDIER
to intervene in places like Wutai. Before
the events of Remake, the Shinra Company
planned to establish a mako reactor in
the nation of Wutai.
This understandably set off alarm bells
with the Wutains because... why wouldn't it?
But more specifically, the Wutains had
seen the way mako reactors were used to
consolidate the Shinra Company's
economic and political control over a
region. This initial resistance, of course, escalated
into a war between Wutai and the Shinra Company.
Now, as an aside if we go through records
of the Shinra Company colonizers--yes, I
said it, colonizers who participated in
the Wutai campaign,
there's the villainous Sephiroth of
course,
but look a little closer and who else do
you see?
Why, it's the fandom's favorite boy Zach
Fair. I'm sorry to break it to you all,
but your fave is a war criminal.
3. Corporations and Government.
Now, a lot of the real life history that
I've spoken about so far was facilitated
with the consent of most of the
governments involved.
In Ludlow, the Rockefellers leveraged
their influence to get the Governor of
Colorado to mobilize the Colorado National
Guard to kill miners and their families.
In Colombia, Chiquita's alleged
collaboration with right-wing death
squads was often condoned by whichever
government was in power at the time.
The British East India Company counted
numerous supporters and shareholders
among members of parliament and waged its bloody
campaign in South Asia with the permission of the crown.
There are probably countless examples I
can add to this section like the issue
of think tanks and lobbyists advancing
corporate interests in the United States.
Did you know that some go as far as to
write model legislation that can be
copied and submitted by lawmakers with
some edits?
Or the age-old tradition of governments
around the world selling national
institutions and natural resources to
corporate interests?
Just look at the privatization of
Chile's education, healthcare, social
security, and copper mines during the brutally
repressive Pinochet regime in the 80s.
When we bring this back to Final Fantasy
VII, we see the broad theme of corporate
power outstripping government power in the
Shinra Company's relationship with Mayor Domino.
His office is placed in an obscure part
of the Shinra Company headquarters, and
his actual governing responsibilities
are very minimal, save for issuing a
temporary state of emergency towards the
beginning of the game.
"The mayor is the best," more like
"capitalism is the worst," am I right folks?
It's easy to dismiss these parallels and
consider the way Midgar and Shinra are
conveyed in final fantasy vii as purely
aesthetic.
You can say the megacity, the futuristic
tech, and Chadley the intern are just
there to evoke cyberpunk coolness, and there's no
intentional engagement with left-wing politics.
But i think it's clear that the writers
of the original game and Remake,
Kazushige Nojima and company, were explicitly
engaging with anti-capitalist themes.
And why?
If the historical parallels alone aren't
enough, what tips the scale?
The answer lies in the ideological
opposition to the Shinra Company, the
political counter-power named after an
environmental phenomenon,
Avalanche.
Chapter 2: A Framework for Avalanche
Barret: "Okay then.
Let's talk about wasteful indulgences.
What is mako? The lifestream!
the lifeblood of the planet--our planet!
But Shinra keeps on slurping it up like
a thirsty dog! Whadda you think's gonna
happen if you don't stop, huh!?"
Frameworks are an important part of any
serious critical analysis, whether it's of a TV
show, a video game, or even events
happening in the world.
For the purpose of this video, let's define
a "framework," also known as a "lens,"
or a "frame of reference," or a "perspective" as the
analytical approach we take when we interpret a subject.
This analytical approach can be informed by a school
of thought, historical patterns, or other ideas.
For example, my discussion of Final
Fantasy VII so far has employed a
framework that's attuned to social and economic
inequalities and their relationship to capitalism.
We'll call this framework
"anti-capitalism."
Now, in reading through Remake's script, I
thought Barret's "wasteful indulgences"
speech to President Shinra and the people
of Midgar was probably the most complete
expression of Avalanche's goals in the
base game.
A planet is a living organism, the Shinra
Company is extracting the planet's
lifeblood, and severe consequences lie ahead
for the planet if that process isn't stopped.
This is why Avalanche must stop the
Shinra Company.
So we can consider the framework of Barret's analysis as
one that's broadly "environmental" - a perspective concerned
with the welfare of the planet. But let's
put a pin in that speech for a second.
There are a number of real-life
left-wing resistance groups which can be
cited as analogues to Avalanche, ranging from Weather
Underground of the United States to the Naxalites in India.
Without getting too far into the weeds
of perfect comparisons, I'd like to look
at an organization that is ostensibly
different from Avalanche in most ways,
save for their concern around
environmental destruction.
Let's talk about Extinction Rebellion UK,
or XR UK for short.
XR UK was established in October 2018 to
combat the ongoing climate emergency. The
group uses a strategy of non-violent
civil disobedience, which includes
tactics such as occupying public spaces,
blocking roads and bridges, and having
its members be arrested en masse to
overwhelm court systems.
Generally, the goal of XR UK demonstrations is to compel
governments to urgently act against climate change.
This can be done through citizen
cssemblies, or bodies of citizens
advising governments on environmental
policy. What hangs over all this is
XR UK's long-standing demand to "Go Beyond
Politics."
In an article for Current Affairs
journalist Erica X Eisen writes that
while the slogan is linked to XR's
demand to create citizens' assemblies,
it's also worded that way to draw in a large amount of
supporters, even those who may consider themselves apolitical.
Eisen states that "Go Beyond Politics"
pivots too far away from a framework
that might explain what's driving the
climate emergency.
Eisen and i view the climate emergency
through an anti-capitalist lens.
We see the primary demand of capitalism.
endless growth. as fundamentally
incompatible with the finite resources
of our planet.
So when i read Barret's "wasteful
indulgences" speech, I'm reminded of
XR UK's "Go Beyond Politics" slogan--they
both have environmental concerns at the
forefront, but the framework is missing that
little extra bit to tie it all together.
It's missing a link to the root cause of
all this: capitalism.
Speaking of, let's take that pin out of
Barret's speech now and test the
limitations of Avalanche's environmental
perspective.
Let's try a thought experiment: we start
by asking ourselves, would Barret's
concerns be sufficiently addressed if
mako reactors were replaced with... oh,
I don't know, *oil wells?*
Would it be too out of line to imagine a
post-Shinra world, where Barret, having
succeeded in the elimination of mako
reactors, is totally fine with burning
oil for energy? A post-Shinra world where
Barrett has a puffer vest and a fishnet shirt?
Do we know enough about Barret's
perspective in Remake to make an
argument for or against oil fields and fishnet
shirts!? Ahem. To be fair to XR UK, the
organization as a whole is intentionally
decentralized so not everyone has to
agree with "Go Beyond Politics" to
participate.
And while "Go Beyond Politics" has had a
presence in XR UK's branding, there are
rank-and-file members who do participate in the
organization with an anti-capitalist framework.
And to be fair to Remake, Barret does
comment on a Shinra employee being blind
to his "corporate masters profiting from
the planet's pain."
in a scene that both adds a smidge of
depth to Avalanche's politics in the base
game, and is a great character moment for
Barret.
Additionally, a member of Avalanche calls
the Shinra Company fascists during a
shootout at the Sector 7 Pillar, which
you know, *I* won't argue with.
With all that said, I think it's useful
for us to go back to the original game.
Let's take a look
Barret: "You saw that village.
It's always the powerless that get
victimized by tyrants like Shinra.
The one's with the power control those
without it. It's just the way of the
world now.
I can't let 'em do that. That's why I
formed AVALANCHE to fight them."
This dialogue is actually inaccessible
in the original game because of a bug
that prevents it from triggering.
You'd read this dialogue in Gongaga,
a settlement in ruin thanks to the explosion of a mako
reactor a little while before the events of the game.
It's a shame that this dialogue is lost
to a lot of players, because it better
establishes Barret's perspective, and by
extension, Avalanche's perspective.
They're not just people who want to
preserve the Lifestream, but they see a
throughline between the Shinra
Company's extraction of mako and the
Shinra Company's oppression of people
around the world.
The InterMISSION chapters take the
spirit of this bit of dialogue,
marries it to that smidge of depth from
Barret's remake dialogue that I
mentioned earlier, and gives us the
following:
Sonon: "Before you got here, I did a little
bit of recon. Found out what they want.
Free elections, workers'
rights, fair distribution of wealth...
... Amazing.
"Are those my glasses?"
Um... No?
But seriously, the dialogue is so explicitly
coded as "leftist" that it's almost in-your-face.
Just as a brief example, the twin demands
of "workers rights" and "fair distribution
of wealth" come up a lot in
Marxist thought.
This school of thought describes the
relationship of "workers"--individuals who
sell their labor to the "ruling class"--
individuals who own the means that
workers use to perform their labor.
Marxism views this relationship as an
unequal arrangement that sees one side
accumulating just enough to continue
living, while the other side hoards and
defends wealth that they didn't create.
The way to upend this relationship is by organizing workers
against the ruling class, which leads to victories like
better working conditions, the redistribution of wealth
from the top to the bottom, and ultimately the end of the
system that relies on this awful
relationship in the first place.
And before you say anything, no, I don't
think i'd call this game "Marxist." I'll go
into this at length a little later in
the video, but there are a few small
issues that prevent me from canonizing
Final Fantasy VII in the cultural
Marxism canon alongside classic works of
art like the Battle of Algiers and...
Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince?
... Whoa...
Apparently, in the extended cut of the
film, the waitress from the introduction
stares directly at the camera and implores
the viewer to support union drives.
Harry Potter and the Waitress at Treats
is now my prevailing headcanon and OTP,
and I think it would make a fine AO3
title, and I hope somebody will get on that
and give us the ending to the series
that we all deserve.
Um...
Moving on...
If we take Barret's dialogue in Remake
alone, there is some plausible
deniability against radical left politics
and the game's depiction of Avalanche.
You might argue "Avalanche is beyond politics, they
just blame the Shinra Company for hurting the planet."
But the context we're given in the
original, InterMISSION and the world we
inhabit very concretely place Avalanche's goals
and actions in an anti-capitalist framework.
To quote Barret in 2022: multinational
corporations are still [quote] destroying
our planet just to build their power and
line their own damn pockets with gold.
[end quote]
Chapter 3: Radical Hearts, Radical Mirrors
We began with this question:
"Is Final Fantasy VII a radical left-wing
game?"
To answer this question I made two
assertions.
First, there is a radical heart to
Final Fantasy VII.
Second, Final Fantasy VII reflects
real-world radical left politics. I think
the *radical heart* of Final Fantasy VII
Is made manifest in the relationships
between Avalanche, Midgar and the Shinra
Company.
Those relationships convey in-universe
ideologies that read to us as radical
because they *reflect* certain historical patterns,
political theory, and the state of the world today.
Let's go over what we've discussed so
far.
1. Avalanche is an organization of
radical environmentalists who interpret
the actions of their enemy through an
anti-capitalist lens.
2. The enemy that avalanche fights
against, the enemy that destroys the
environment and oppresses people around
the world, is the Shinra Company.
3. The monument to Shinra's Global
campaign of environmental destruction
and domination of its inhabitants, the
place that puts the "under" in "underclass,"
the expired pizza that rots the land--
is the city of Midgar.
This ever beating heart propels much of
what happens in Remake proper.
We know that the shinra company's
process of accumulating wealth has had
tremendous consequences like war, murder,
kidnapping, massacres, environmental
destruction, and economic inequality.
We know that these consequences brought
Cloud, Barret, Tifa Aerith and Red XIII to
Midgar at different points of their lives.
We know that after arriving in Midgar,
the lives of these characters converge
in part because of additional shinra
company fuckery during the events of Remake.
But is that the end of this video?
Well, if we want to absolutely,
definitively, and concretely conclude
that Remake has the promise of radical
left politics, it behooves us to see
where Remake falls short of that promise.
Let's look at two examples, starting with
a closer examination of Barret Wallace.
Chapter 4: The Trouble with
Barret Wallace
What does it mean that most of the
radical Barret quotes I cited in the
last chapter came from the original game?
When you look at the equivalent sections
in Remake's script--the sections in which
you'd expect Barret to make the same
indictments of inequality except in 60 frames per
second with full voice-acting-- they're not there.
Consider the train ride after the
bombing of Reactor Number 1.
In the original game, that's where the "fucking
'pizza'" conversation happens between Barret and Cloud.
We're specifically told that lack of money and
love of the land keep the poor on the lower plate.
In Remake this conversation shifts much
of the focus to the mako reactor's...
adverse effects on soil and air.
Consider also the aftermath of the
Sector 7 plate fall.
In the original game, Tifa wonders aloud
if Shinra razed the Sector and
massacred its people because of
Avalanche.
Barret replies that the atrocity is
Shinra's fault and it's "always been
the Shinra" -- they're
destroying the planet for profit.
In Remake, Tifa expresses the same
sentiment, and Barret again emphasizes
that the massacre is the Shinra
Company's fault...
but the more radical line about profit
is excised.
It's like Remakes writers took the
original character's anti-capitalist
framework and replaced it with the less severe
"environmental" framework we discussed earlier.
Or, to use a more relatable analogy for
today's generation, the proletarian
Barret of the original game has been
replaced by the renegade Barret in Remake.
... get it?
like the, uh,
like the 1918 polemic that Vladimir
Lenin wrote against Karl Kautsky?
Um...
make sure you like and subscribe for
more topical political content.
When we consider the way Remake reins
in Barret's anti-capitalist rhetoric,
and the way the game focuses more on
Avalanche's "collateral damage" in the form
of Midgar residents being harmed and property
being destroyed compared to the original game,
we should keep in mind that this
political shift was done deliberately.
Here's what Remake's Director Motomu
Toriyama had to say in an interview:
"... when the original came out we were all
pretty young and things like 'is it
really right to destroy the mako
reactors to save the planet?' didn't
really cross our minds at all. However,
with the remake a lot of things have
happened in the real world, so we as the
developers have a responsibility to
figure out how to make things relate as
well as how far to go."
As a result of this shift,
Remake Barret's strongest indictment of the
Shinra Company's accumulation of wealth--
their "profiting from the planet's pain"--
is in a single line in a missable cutscene
in the Shinra Company Headquarters.
We also see a notable divergence from
the original game's plot and Remake
the version of Avalanche that we see at
the start of the game is no longer a
group that Barret founded, it's now a much larger
organization comprised of a headquarters and multiple cells.
Avalanche HQ considers Barret's cell
too extreme, and by the start of the game,
his group operates as a splinter cell detached
from the larger Avalanche organization.
I'm tentatively watching to see how this
plot update plays out in future
installments, but in the context of
Remake and InterMISSION
I think it's not the greatest attempt at
adding nuance.
My bone to pick with this plot thread is
political: we never see what the more
"moderate" strategy of addressing the Shinra Company's
runaway oppression and environmental destruction looks like.
Moreover, the final word on the
ideological conflict between the more
extreme and moderate sides of Avalanche
is given to us by Sonon in InterMISSION.
Sonon: "Hey, about what you said earlier."
Yuffie: "Which was...?"
Sonon: "About Avalanche--how it's changed." Yuffie: "Oh. That."
Sonon: "These people are too
soft. But those splinter cell guys?
*They* sound like the ones we should have
teamed up with. Don'tcha think?"
For what it's worth Sonon... I think so.
One other area that could have actually
used more nuance in the final product
was Barret's blaxploitation-inspired...
everything.
That's, right I couldn't make a video
about the radical politics of Final
Fantasy VII without addressing the
elephant in the room:
Barret: "Duhn-duhn-duhn-*duhn*, duhn duhn, *duhn*-da-*duhn*!" "Suck on this!"
"Where could they be going...?
Embarking on an adventure to find some
treasure!?" "Suck on this!" "This pump's
sole purpose is to drain the planet dry.
While you sleep, while you eat, while you
shit--it's here, sucking up mako.
It doesn't rest and it doesn't care!
You do realize what mako is, don't you?
Mako is the lifeblood of our world. The
planet bleeds green like you and me bleed red.
The hell you think's gonna happen when
it's all gone, huh!? Answer me!
You gonna stand there and pretend you
can't hear the planet crying out in
pain?" "Open wide!
And suck on this!"
Black representation in mainstream media
has traditionally had a lot of problems.
How do i define the scope of mainstream
media--
Is a game from Japan really a part of
mainstream media in the English-speaking world?
Well, I live in the United States, and
within the past 10 or more years, our
national conversations around literature,
movies, television shows, and video games
have included work from other places
around the world.
This isn't the result of happenstance,
but intentional.
For example, the 2021 anti-capitalist
sensation Squid Game didn't cross over
from people living in South Korea to a
U.S. audience by word-of-mouth,
but according to creator Hwang Dong-hyuk, it was
intentionally written and marketed for a global audience.
How do i define the problems of black
representation in media?
The typical tropes have been well
described for over a century by scholars,
by journalists, by activists... by regular
folks who consume art. There's enough
writing on the history and problems of
black representation and media to fill
up several Hell Houses, but I liked the
CBC's brief exploration of black
representation in Hollywood films if you
want to dip your toes.
Feel free to recommend readings in the
comments as well, for me and other viewers.
The issues with Remake's most prominent
instance of black representation have
been outlined by writers such as Jeffrey Rousseau
in Ars Technica, and Norris Howard in Checkpoint XP.
These issues go as far as the way
Barret's hair is rendered, as clarified
in an illuminating conversation led by
Austin Walker on Twitter.
In short, Remake's Barret exhibits
exaggerated, relatively more emotive
speech that evokes a preacher from the
U.S. South.
He channels the trope of the big scary
black man at points.
He also functions as comic relief by
doing things like singing Stamp the
dog's theme song
and the game's victory fanfare.
Prior to Remake, Barret already carried
some baggage because of the way fans
associated him with Mr. T
from the popular 80s U.S. television
series A-Team. This association has been
acknowledged by Final Fantasy VII
character designer and writer Tetsuya
Nomura who wrote in 2006: "Barret is
often compared to a certain 'A-Team'
member."
Interesting to note is that Barret's
Mr.T-esque dialogue quirks in the original--
for example his tendency to call people
"fools"--
appears to be a consequence of the
English language localization.
In playing the original in both English
and Japanese at the same time writer
Tim Rogers in Kotaku describes Barret coming off as
more of a serious military man in the original Japanese.
For all of Remake Barret's good scenes
and dialogue, the Remake team did a
pretty poor job at shaking off this
baggage.
While he isn't emulating Mr. T anymore, as
Jeffrey Rousseau points out, his voice
still oozes black exploitation
characters of the 70s. I've seen attempts
by commenters to downplay the issue in one of
the referenced articles and the Twitter thread.
The issue is hand waved as "Japanese
developers are making a product for
Japanese people first and foremost, they
can't be faulted for messing up Barret,"
"Japanese media has a poor track record
in terms of the depiction of
non-Japanese ethnicity," "The concerns
about good representation of black
people is a U.S. conceit that's out of touch
with the rest of the world," and so on.
But we're not talking about sheltered
babies who happened to put together a
video game that became an international
hit.
This is a corporation that, despite being
at least peripherally aware of negative
associations around Barret, still made a deliberate
decision to convey a black character in a stereotypical way.
As Austin Walker writes: "You cannot give
Barret a blaxploitation voice, make him
speak with black slang and then pretend
that you don't owe anything to blackness."
Remake's failure to better engage with
the blackness it borrows from
unfortunately fits the same pattern of
failure in mainstream media.
There's one last facet of Remake Barret
that I'll talk about, and it lies at the
intersection of two dimensions we've
already talked about.
Let's look at a passage from political
scientist Cedric Robinson's 1998 essay
"Black Exploitation and the
Misrepresentation of Liberation."
Unfortunately this is the only work in
this video that's paywalled: the essay is
available in the collection Cedric J.
Robinson: On Racial Capitalism, Black
Internationalism, and Cultures of
Resistance. If you have access to
academic search engines, *any* academic search engines,
you can find the original article by plugging in the title.
I've transcribed the passage most
relevant to this discussion in full:
One of the most effective and clever
manoeuvres of the Blaxploitation genre
was the appropriation and representation
of Angela Davis's public image.
This manipulation, of course, was of a
piece with the commercial cinema's
translation of the mass black rebellion which
occurred near the end of the Civil Rights era...
independent and then established
film-makers trivialised the troubled
activists of the movement into the now
familiar male counter-revolutionary
creatures: the male prostitute ('Sweetback');
the vigilante cops ('Gravedigger Jones' and
'Coffin Ed Johnson'); the dope pusher ('Shaft');
and the gangster ('Black Caesar', etc.)
... Film however transported Davis's form
from a representation of a revolutionist to
that of an erotic black nationalist,
largely devoid of historical
consciousness. This was achieved by eviscerating the
original's intellectual sophistication, political and
organisational context, doctrinal
commitments, and most tellingly, her
critique of capitalist society and its
employment of gender, race and class."
Robinson goes on to specifically describe the eroticization
of Angela Davis in blaxploitation films through
characters played by Pam Grier and
Rosalind Cash--
but what we're concerned about when it
comes to Barret is the idea of black
militants having their own image and
their own systemic critiques caricatured
when they're translated from real life
to film.
When I look at Barret and all of his
incarnations, original, Remake or
otherwise, it's hard not to see
Robinson's observations being practiced
even if the underlying context and
authorial intentions aren't 100% aligned
with blaxploitation filmmakers of the
70s,
I think there's a throughline between
the archetypical images of black
militants in the United States from the
60s and 70s and Barret.
For the sake of my argument let's place
the start of this throughline at the
real-life black radicals of the 60s and
70s.
those real-life people are transformed
into political caricatures in the
blaxploitation films of the 70s and 80s.
One soon-to-be famous actor named Mr. T
makes his Hollywood debut in the
blaxploitation film Penitentiary II in
1982 before becoming a breakout star with his role
as Clubber Lang in Rocky III later that same year.
Mr. T goes on to achieve lasting
international recognition with the
starring role on A-Team as B.A. Baracas
from 1983 to 1987.
The original Final Fantasy VII is released
in 1997, about a decade after the end of
A-Team, and one of the first party
members you meet in the game, one of the
first party members conceived for the
game, is Barret Wallace. Here, we have a
character who evokes Mr. T visually, channels Mr. T
and blaxploitation characters in his dialogue,
and has some of the anti-capitalist politics of
those real-life black radicals from the 60s and 70s.
I presented this timeline in a linear
way, but the argument is not intended to
be a straight trip from "point A" to "point
B" -- it's more of a confluence of factors,
some connected, like black radicals and
their blaxploitation counterparts, and
some parallel, like the inauguration of
Mr. T into the popular consciousness.
But I do see Barrett Wallace as a result
of this confluence.
From 1997, let's skip straight to 2021,
where the somewhat de-politicized
Barret of the original game has become the
even more depoliticized Barret of Remake.
And remember this depoliticization is
relative to his real-life radical
progenitors, not a total judgment of the
two Barrets' politics.
This contrast really helps bring into
high relief the idea, partly informed by
Dr. Robinson, that the act of translating
revolutionary politics to mainstream
media causes those politics to be watered
down or caricatured in the final product.
I guess there's one outstanding question
that i've been eliding this whole time:
"Is Barret's portrayal in Final Fantasy
VII Remake racist?"
*Yes*
Chapter 5: People of Midgar
I said earlier that there are a few
small issues that prevent me, a person of
authority, from canonizing Final Fantasy
VII as a Marxist game.
Let's get the obvious issues out of the
way:
1. Neither Nojima, Nomura, Toriyama,
nor any of the senior production staff
involved in the Compilation of Final
Fantasy VII have ever publicly
communicated an overtly left-wing intent or inspiration
in conveying the world of Final Fantasy VII.
As a bit of a leftist myself I often
have to remind myself that sometimes,
popular media can just make radical
points without necessarily being on the
side of international communist
revolution.
Like, it's definitely okay for John
Oliver to point out contradictions in
capitalism in his weekly show without taking that
extra half-step and indicting the whole damn system.
It's okay for John Oliver to present
issues in such a way that the viewer is
guided towards interrogating the system that
created those issues--the system being capitalism--
without John Oliver himself actually
condemning capitalism.
It's OK for John Oliver to not be
communist, okay?
2. The original's overt anti-capitalist themes
fall off a bit after the Midgar section.
We'll see how the Remake series handles
these themes in subsequent releases, but
from what I remember of the original, the game's
themes pivot to Cloud's past, Aerith's future,
and the pursuit of Sephiroth, or the Path
of Sephirot if you're a Xenogears fan.
Does that even make sense?
Let me know in the comments, will you?
Shinra largely leaves the foreground for
the next part of the game, with a few
exceptions like the Corel Village plot and
the backstory around the Wutai side-quests.
By far the largest demerit I could levy against the
argument that "Remake is a Marxist game" is this:
3. The people of Midgar don't participate
in their own liberation. To begin
unpacking this, I ask you this question:
can you recall any instances of regular
ole' residents of Midgar in Final
Fantasy VII organizing themselves?
We don't see people clamoring to join
Avalanche.
The most grassroots form of activity we see is
the work of the Neighborhood Watch in Sector 7,
a community defense organization that
patrols and exterminates monsters.
Meanwhile, we're told that Avalanche
levies demands like workers' rights, we
never get more information about
Avalanche's praxis around these
demands, nor information on how Midgar residents
participate in advocating these demands for themselves.
There isn't a great sense that the
residents of Midgar stand in solidarity
with Avalanche, something that's
especially made apparent in the
incidental dialogue from Midgar
residents after the Sector 7 plate fall.
So we conclude that Avalanche is the
primary, if not sole group of people
agitating for radical change in Midgar.
We also conclude that Avalanche and
Midgar residents don't have much cross-pollination
by way of collaboration going on.
This is just not a Marxist relation nor is
it a strong portrayal of radical politics.
You'll remember from our discussion of Marxist thought
that workers are named the agents of radical change.
To paraphrase the Communist Manifesto:
"Communists have no interest separate and
apart from those of the workers as a whole...
The immediate aim of the communists is
the formation of the workers into a class,
overthrow of ruling class supremacy and
conquest of political power by workers."
There's no doubt that the Avalanche members we know
intimately are reflective of workers in Midgar, with
Biggs being a former teacher, Jesse being
a former actor, and Tifa being a bartender,
Cloud being a Shinra Public...
SOLDIER First Class.
But all the revolutionary activity that
happens in Midgar begins and ends with
Avalanche. We don't see other Midgar residents
get involved or become radicalized by Avalanche.
Regular ole' Midgar residents don't exhibit any
revolutionary agency towards their own liberation.
There's no self-determination!
I know what you're thinking: "a work doesn't need
to be 'Marxist' to be radical" -- and I agree.
I do think Marxism is a useful lens
through which we can assess a work's
radical qualities, especially given the way
these games evoke anti-capitalist ideas.
Deploying that lens magnifies that last
demerit I described - that the people who
would benefit from their own liberation
are never significantly involved or
represented among the ranks of Avalanche,
who have taken on the mantle of
liberator. There is probably some radical
tradition or theory that reconciles this
imbalanced relationship to make it work,
but it's hard for me to co-sign the idea
that a handful of special folks
shepherding the rest of us into a
brighter future is a particularly
radical idea.
With that, I guess it's about time we
answered that one question, isn't it?
Chapter 6:
The Answer
We've reached the end of our journey
together and look how far we've come:
we've vivisected a radical heart, we've
shattered a radical mirror,
we've bullied the man with the machine
gun arm, and most importantly we've saved
an innocent video game from being
labeled "Marxist."
I'm sure you're clamoring to hear a definitive
answer to the question in the title of the video:
"Is Final Fantasy VII a Radical Left-Wing
Game?"
But before we put our stamp on the question once and
for all, I think it's worth noting a couple of things:
First, a handful of you, including my
Developmental Editor Elizabeth
might be annoyed that I spent a lot of
time talking about the "Content" of Final
Fantasy VII without even touching the
"Form" of Final Fantasy VII.
To quote Elizabeth's notes on this video:
"I think part of the analysis of a work
of art's politics is not just its content
[what the game is about, the issues it
deals with, what the plot and characters
show about the politics of the work, etc.]
but its form. For instance, what kind of
narrative it is, how does its genre
influence the story being told, what kind
of interactions does it create with its
audience, what kind of 'subject' interacts
with it and interprets it and how;
also who produces it, how it's produced
why societies turn to certain kinds of art
(such as video games) at certain times."
The relationship of "Form" and "Content"
comes out of the writings of G. W. F. Hegel
and Marxist thinkers like Theodor
Adorno, and it's definitely something i
could stand to learn more about.
I'm leaving this as an open thread for
folks to discuss and I might pick it
back up for a new video in the future.
Second, let's be mindful of our tendency
as left-wing consumers and critics to
impute certain political conclusions to
works of art that we enjoy.
Take the statement by English professor
Nicola Nixon:
"The conflation of aesthetic appreciation
and good politics surfaces in certain
critics as a form of leftist wish
fulfillment... in other words, if one likes
the fiction, it must necessarily involve the
articulation of a perceptible, revolutionary project."
Definitely a mood. I often have to stop
myself from running too wild with my
left-wing wish fulfillment when I
brainstorm and write up outlines for my
videos. As a leftist, I think it's fun to
recognize and appreciate radical
left-wing elements in a work, whether
it's anti-capitalist themes, rhetoric
about things like "workers' rights," and
relations that mirror relations we see in history.
I think I would conclude that Final
Fantasy VII doesn't use its radical
left-wing elements as set dressing, but makes those
elements crucial to the existence of its world:
look towards Midgar, the Shinra Company,
and Avalanche as examples.
That said, having reviewed the body of
evidence,
I don't think Final Fantasy VII - the original, Remake Part
1, any iteration - can be called a radical left-wing game.
I don't think there's enough being done
by the game to synthesize its left-wing
elements into a conclusion about the
nature of our world.
The game doesn't have to be an
on-the-nose satire to achieve this,
but it's telling to me that the game's
various anti-capitalist aspects tend to
converge towards the conclusion that
Shinra is the problem and not capitalism
generally, limiting the scope of the game's
message to a specific evil inside of its own world.
However, I will say that Final Fantasy
VII is a damn fine game,
leftist gamers don't have to limit themselves to
ideologically pure or even ideologically coherent games,
and you can literally operate a sewer system's
water pump with your girlfriend in Remake.
Play the game.
play InterMISSION.
Just go and do it.
And most importantly, get involved with a
left organization in your area.
If you live in the United States, look up
who's active in your area, see what kind
of work they do around the specific issues that
you're interested in whether it's the environment,
anti-racism or abortion rights--and see
how you can get involved.
The good organizations will typically
have some sort of political education
program which might cover some of the real life
events and topics I've discussed in this video.
If you live in the United States, the
Democratic Socialists of America has
chapters in states across the country --
shoutout to the AFROSOC caucus.
Don't discount smaller groups either,
even if it's just a once a month reading
group -- it's so useful to learn with a group of people,
to have conversations and debates, to become activated!
Because everything I've described--from
the exploitation of the poor, to the
destruction of the environment-- can
only be stopped if we organize ourselves.
To paraphrase Barret and Aerith at
different points in Remake:
"We don't want to look back one day and
wish we'd done it differently
right here, right now, we need to keep
moving forward,
so we can say we did *everything* we could."
[Music]